Inventory of the Benjamin Stoddert Ewell Papers 1784-1934
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Benjamin Stoddert Ewell Papers, 1784-1934.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 Ew3
1,256 items.
This group of 1,256 items and one bound volume, dated 1784-1934, consists chiefly of letters and papers of the Ewell family of Virginia. Many personal letters of Benjamin S. Ewell are included.
Benjamin Stoddert Ewell;; Elizabeth Stoddert Ewell, 1794-1859;; Elizabeth S. Ewell, b. 1814?;; Richard Stoddert Ewell;; Hugh Blair Grigsby;; Moses Drury Hoge;; Joseph E. Johnston;; D. H. Mahan;; Elizabeth S. Ewell Scott;; Francis Henney Smith;; William Stoddert;; John Tyler;; Julia Gardiner Tyler;; Lyon Gardiner Tyler;; Henry A. Wise.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 1,128 items, 12/31/1935.
Gift: 100 items, 03/30/1936.
Gift: 25 items, 05/1/1957.
Gift: 1 item, 04/1973.
Gift: 1 item, 03/1973.
Acc. No. 2001,14A; Gift: 1 item, 04/14/2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Benjamin Stoddert Ewell was born in Georgetown, D. C., 10 June 1810, the son of Thomas Ewell and Elizabeth Stoddert. He graduated from United States Military Academy and taught there. He taught at Hampden- Sydney College and at Washington College (now Washington and Lee University). In 1848, he was elected professor of mathematics and acting president of College of William and Mary and in 1854, became president. He was colonel of 32nd Virginia Infantry Regiment and later assistant adjutant-general to Joseph E. Johnston. He was president of William and Mary 1854-1888 and died 1894. He was the brother of Richard Stoddert Ewell, had another brother, William Stoddert, a sister Elizabeth S. Ewell and a daughter Elizabeth S. Ewell Scott.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains materials dated 1784-1934. It includes correspondence, legal papers, and accounts, chiefly 1830-1892, of Benjamin S. Ewell, professor at the U.S. Military Academy, Hampden-Sydney College, Washington and Lee College, and the College of William and Mary (which he served as acting president, 1848-1849, and president, 1854-1888). Also, letters from Ewell during the Civil War when he was assistant adjutant-general to Gen. Joseph E. Johnston. Among the correspondents are members of the Tyler, Ewell, Campbell, and Brown families of Virginia and Tennessee. Includes memorandum book on Ewell family by Elizabeth S. Ewell.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection has been organized into 3 Series. Series 1 includes letters arranged alpabetically by writer; Series 2 includes papers; and Series 3 includes an addition to the collection.
Arrangement
This collection of papers is arranged alphabetically. A uniform entry has been adopted for each name, and persons of the same name have been identified and distinguished from each other by indicating their relationship to Benjamin S. Ewell or other persons. For example, the entry Brown (Harriot S.) is used for letters signed H. S. Brown and Hattie, and the entry Ewell (Elizabeth), daughter of Benjamin S. Ewell, is used for letters signed Lizzy Ewell or simply Lizzy.
Additional Bibliographic Material
Bibliography
Chapman, Anne W. Benjamin Stoddert Ewell: A Biography 1984. Ph D. Dissertation, College of William and Mary.
Call Number: LD6051 .W5m Hist., 1984, C33
Controlled Access Terms
Index Terms
Persons:
Ewell, Benjamin Stoddert, 1810-1894.; Ewell, Elizabeth Stoddert, 1794-1859.; Ewell, Elizabeth S., b. 1814?; Ewell, Richard Stoddert, 1817-1872.; Grigsby, Hugh Blair, 1806- 1881.; Hoge, Moses Drury, 1818-1899.; Johnston, Joseph E. (Joseph Eggleston), 1807-1891.; Mahan, D. H. (Dennis Hart), 1802-1871.; Scott, Elizabeth S. Ewell, b. 1841.; Smith, Francis Henney, 1812-1890.; Stoddert, William.; Tyler, John, 1819-1896.; Tyler, Julia Gardiner, 1820- 1889.; Tyler, Lyon Gardiner, 1853-1935.; Wise, Henry A. (Henry Alexander), 1806-1876.
Family Names:
Ewell family.
Subjects:
College of William and Mary--History--19th century.; Hampden-Sydney College.; Washington and Lee University.; Williamsburg (Va.)--History--19th century.; United States-- History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Contents List
  Series 1: Letters
- Letters, 1784-1934. (Folder 1-19)
  - Letters: A-B, 1784-1934 (Folder 1)
    - Alden (B. R.), at West Point, New York, to B. S. Ewell, at York, Pennsylvania, 15 November 1838. (Folder 1)
    - T. McD. Goldsbrough on behalf of Alexandria & Orange Railroad, to B. S. Ewell, 3 August 1850. (Folder 1)
    - Alvord (Benjamin), at Transylvania University, Lexington, Kentucky, to Benjamin S. Ewell, at Prince Edward Court House, Virginia, 6 December 1840. (Folder 1)
    - Anderson (J. R.), at Richmond, to Prof. George E. Dabney, 24 May 1854. (Folder 1)
      Letter recommending Benjamin S. Ewell for a professorship.
    - Anderson and Doan, at Washington, D.C., to William S. Caruthers, at Olympia, Washington, 16 December 1883. (Folder 1)
    - Armistead (C. P.), at Williamsburg, Virginia, to Col. Benjamin S. Ewell, at Ewell's Station,[James City County], 27 November 1889., 2 letters, one including a receipt. (Folder 1)
    - Armstrong (George D.), at Norfolk, Virginia, to the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia, 12 June 1854. (Folder 1)
    - Bailey (J. W.), professor of chemistry, United States Military Academy, West Point, New York, to whom it may concern, 8 April 1848. (Folder 1)
    - Bailey (J. W.), at West Point, New York, to Benjamin S. Ewell, 26 September 1851. (Folder 1)
    - Bailey (J. W.), at West Point, New York, to George E. Dabney, at Richmond, 12 June 1854. (Folder 1)
      Note: This letter includes a recommendation for Benjamin S. Ewell as a professor, signed by five professors at the United States Military Academy.
    - Bane (Ragland A.), at Keily Field, Texas, to Mrs. R.W. Crawford, at Williamsburg, Virginia Postmarked, 4 February 1918. (Folder 1)
    - Barlow (R. G.), at Williamsburg, Virginia, to Col. Benjamin S. Ewell, 21 March 1894. (Folder 1)
    - Bartlett (William H. C.), at West Point, New York, to Benjamin S. Ewell, at York, Pennsylvania, 25 January 1839. (Folder 1)
    - Beckwith (Anne L.), at Sunny Side, to her cousin [ ? ], 12 May 1857. (Folder 1)
    - Berkeley (Alice Scott), at Mayland, to Elizabeth Ewell, daughter of Benjamin S. Ewell, 3 July 1863. (Folder 1)
    - Berry (Bety) to Rebecca Lowndes Ewell, at Greenwich, Prince William County, Virginia Postmarked Bladensburg, Maryland, 1 December 1838. (Folder 1)
    - Blodgett (E. W.), at Yokohama, Japan, to Mrs. Elizabeth Ewell Scott, 10 September 1894. (Folder 1)
    - Bonner (William G.), at Warrenton, Warren County, Georgia, to Lt. Benjamin S. Ewell, at York, Pennsylvania, 20 August 1836. (Folder 1)
    - Bragg (Bettie), at St. Louis, Missouri, to Elizabeth S. Ewell, sister of Benjamin S. Ewell, at Georgetown, D.C., No date. (Folder 1)
    - Braxton (Corbin) to Benjamin S. Ewell, at Buckland, Prince William County, Virginia Postmarked Richmond, Virginia, 24 July 1848. (Folder 1)
    - Brewster (Benjamin Harris), at Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to Benjamin S. Ewell, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 1 May 1886. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to Elizabeth Ewell, sister of Benjamin S. Ewell, at Georgetown, D.C., 23 January 1872. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Springville [i.e. Spring Hill], Tennessee, to Rev. M. D. Hoge, at Richmond, 23 January 1872. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to his cousin, [ ? ], 3 February 1872. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to his cousin, Benjamin S. Ewell, 28 February 1872. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to Benjamin S. Ewell, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 11 March 1872. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to his cousin, [ ? ], 26 March 1872. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Nashville, Tennessee, to his cousin, [ ? ], 26 March 1872. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to Col. Benjamin S. Ewell, 28 March 1872. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to Elizabeth Ewell Scott, 10 April 1872. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to his cousin, Benjamin S. Ewell., 4 items. (Folder 1)
      - Letter, 13 April 1872. (Folder 1)
      - Letter, 4 May 1872. (Folder 1)
      - Letter, 12 July 1872. (Folder 1)
      - Letter, [1872]. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to Benjamin S. Ewell, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 27 June 1873. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to B. S. Ewell, 27 December 1873. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to his cousin, [ ? ], 24 November 1884. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to Elizabeth Ewell Scott, December 1884-February 1888., 2 items. (Folder 1)
      - Letter, 27 December 1884. (Folder 1)
      - Letter, 7 February 1888. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Mexico, Missouri, to Elizabeth Ewell Scott, 11 Jan 188[?]. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Campbell), at Spring Hill, Tennessee, to Elizabeth Ewell Scott, 2 November 1891. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (E.H.), at Richmond, to Elizabeth Ewell, daughter of Benjamin S. Ewell. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Harriot S.) to Elizabeth Ewell, daughter of Benjamin S. Ewell. Lizinka C. Brown to Elizabeth Ewell.(On same sheet.), 23 September 1856. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Harriot S.), at New York, to Elizabeth Ewell, 17 July 1860. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Harriot S.), at Charlottesville, Virginia, to Elizabeth Ewell, October-November 1863., 4 items. (Folder 1)
      - Letter, 12 October 1863. (Folder 1)
      - Letter, 23 October 1863. (Folder 1)
      - Letter, 5 November 1863. (Folder 1)
      - Letter, 17 November 1863. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Harriot S.), at Morton Hall, [Prince Edward County, Virginia], to Elizabeth Ewell, 19 January [1864]. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Harriot S.) to Elizabeth Ewell., Two letters. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Harriot S.), at Kinlock, [Alabama], to Elizabeth Ewell. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Harriot S.), at Morton Hall, to Elizabeth Ewell., Two letters. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Harriot S.), at Nashville, Tennessee, to Elizabeth Ewell, n.d., Two letters. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Harriot S.), at Washington, to Elizabeth Ewell. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Harriot S.) to [ ? ]. See also Harriot S. Turner. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Lizinka C.), at Nashville, Tennessee, to her cousin, [ ? ], 26 January 1850. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Lizinka C.), at Nashville, Tennessee, to B. S. Ewell, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 9 June 1850. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Lizinka C.), at Nashville, Tennessee, to Rebecca Ewell, 28 October 1855. (Folder 1)
    - Brown (Lizinka C.), to her aunt,[ ? ], No date. (Folder 1)
    - Brown, (Percy), at Ewell Farm, Spring Hill, Tennessee, to Bessie Scott Crawford, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 15 October 1917. (Folder 1)
    - Burgess (B.J.), at Wilmington, North Carolina, to Benjamin S. Ewell, at Williamsburg, Virginia (See William and Mary Papers.), 2 November 1878. (Folder 1)
    - Burnet (David G.), at Galveston, to [ ? ], 25 June 1860. (Folder 1)
  - Letters: C-D, 1784-1934 (Folder 2)
    - Campbell (Harriot), at Nashville, Tennessee, to her sister, Mrs. Elizabeth Ewell, mother of Benjamin S. Ewell, at Greenwich, Prince William County, Virginia. A short unsigned letter. (On same sheet.) Thomas Ewell, to his mother, Mrs. Elizabeth Ewell. (On same sheet.), 15 January 1836. (Folder 2)
    - Campbell (Harriot), at Nashville, Tennessee, to Mrs. Elizabeth Ewell, at Greenwich, Prince William County, Virginia. Lizinka Campbell to her aunt, Mrs. Elizabeth Ewell. (On same sheet.) Thomas Ewell to Mrs. Elizabeth Ewell. (On same sheet.), 31 October 1838. (Folder 2)
    - Campbell (Harriot), at Nashville, Tennessee, to Mrs. Elizabeth Ewell, at Greenwich, Prince William County, Virginia. Thomas Ewell to Mrs. Elizabeth Ewell (On same sheet.), 9 April 1839. (Folder 2)
    - Campbell (Harriot), at Nashville, Tennessee, to Mrs. Elizabeth Ewell, at Greenwich, Prince William County, Virginia. Thomas Ewell to Mrs. Elizabeth Ewell. (On same sheet.), No date. (Folder 2)
    - Carr (James P.), in France, to Mrs. R.W. Crawford, at Williamsburg, Virginia, January 1918-April 1918., 2 items. (Folder 2)
      - Letter, 21 January 1918. (Folder 2)
      - Letter, 1 April 1918. (Folder 2)
    - Chase (George B.), at Boston, Mass., to Elizabeth Ewell, sister of Benjamin S. Ewell, at Georgetown, D.C., 9 July 1885. (Folder 2)
    - Christian (John B.), at Williamsburg, Virginia, to H. B. Tomlin, 15 June 1854. (Folder 2)
    - Cocke (Philip St. George), at Richmond, to George E. Dabney, at Richmond, 26 May 1854. (Folder 2)
    - Cocke (Philip St. George), Virginia Military Institute, to Benjamin Ewell, 30 June 1855(9). (Folder 2)
    - [Confederate State of America] Medical Director's Office, at Dalton, Georgia, to Col. B. S. Ewell, 29 April 1864. (Folder 2)
    - Conway (Richard Moncure), at Conway Farm, near Peake's Cross Roads P.O., Spottsylvania County, Virginia, to Benjamin S. Ewell, at Williamsburg, Virginia, April 1883-March 1884., 5 items. (Folder 2)
      - Letter, 18 April 1883., 2 copies. (Folder 2)
      - Letter, 10 September 1883. (Folder 2)
      - Letter, 19 September 1883. (Folder 2)
      - Letter, 25 February 1884. (Folder 2)
      - Letter, 12 March 1884. (Folder 2)
    - Courtenay (Edward H.), at the University of Virginia, to Col. R. McCandlish, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 25 April 1848. (Folder 2)
      Letter recommending Benjamin S. Ewell for a professorship. (See William and Mary Papers.)
    - Craik (James), at Louisville, Benjamin S. Ewell, at Williamsburg, Virginia (See William and Mary Papers.), January 1874-September 1876., 3 items. (Folder 2)
      - Letter, 6 January 1874. (Folder 2)
      - Letter, 23 January 1874. (Folder 2)
      - Letter, 2 September 1876. (Folder 2)
    - Crawford (R. M.), at Baltimore, Maryland, to Mrs. R.M. Crawford, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 15 May 1912. (Folder 2)
    - Crittenden (A. P.), at Lexington, to B. S. Ewell, at York, Pennsylvania, 28 May 1838. (Folder 2)
    - Crittenden (A. P.), at Charlestown, Virginia, to B. S. Ewell, at York, Pennsylvania, No date. (Folder 2)
    - Crittenden (A. P.), at Charlestown, Virginia, to B. S. Ewell, or T. P. Chiffelle, at York, Pennsylvania, No date. (Folder 2)
    - Crittenden (A. P.), at Lancaster, Kentucky, to B. S. Ewell, at York, Pennsylvania, No date. (Folder 2)
    - Crump (William W.) to Col. Benjamin S. Ewell, 11 March 1871. (Folder 2)
    - Crump (William W.), at Richmond, Virginia, to Richard A. Wise, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 20 June 1894. (Folder 2)
    - Crump (Judge and Mrs. William W.) to Col. Benjamin Ewell. (Folder 2)
      An invitation to the marriage reception of their daughter.
      Enclosures: Two cards, Emmy A. Crump and William B. Lightfoot.
    - Custis (Kate W.), at Williamsburg, Virginia, to Elizabeth S. Ewell, daughter of Benjamin S. Ewell, at Spring Hill, Maury County, Tennessee, 27 September 1867. (Folder 2)
    - Dabney (George E.), at Lexington, Virginia, to Benjamin S. Ewell, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 10 March 1851. (Folder 2)
    - Dabney (George E.), at Richmond, to Joseph C. Cabell, at Warminster, [Nelson County], Virginia, 24 May 1854. (Folder 2)
    - Dabney (George E.), at Richmond, to Fleming B. Miller, at Fincastle, Botetourt County, Virginia, 8 June 1854. (Folder 2)
    - Dame (W.M.), at Baltimore, Maryland, to Mrs. [ ? ] Turner, 24 March 1890. (Folder 2)
    - Davies (Charles), at Hartford, Connecticut, to Benjamin Ewell, 26 October 1838. (Folder 2)
    - Davies (Charles), at Hartford, to Benjamin S. Ewell, at York, Pennsylvania, 2 November 1838. (Folder 2)
    - Davies (Charles), at New York, to John Tyler, 27 April 1848. (Folder 2)
    - Davies (Charles), at Fish Kill Landing, New York, to George E. Dabney, 13 June 1854. (Folder 2)
    - Davies (Charles), at Fish Kill Landing, New York, to William C. Reeves, 13 June 1854. (Folder 2)
    - Davies (Charles), at Fish Kill Landing, New York, to [ ? ] Smith, 13 June 1854. (Folder 2)
    - Davies (Charles), at Fish Kill Landing, to Andrew Stevenson, 13 June 1854. (Folder 2)
    - Davies (Charles), at Fish Kill Landing, to the Visitors of the University of Virginia, 13 June 1854. (Folder 2)
    - Davies (Charles), at Fish Kill Landing, to B. S. Ewell, 24 April 1856. (Folder 2)
    - Davis (V. Jefferson), at Beauvoir House, Beauvoir, Miss., to Benjamin S. Ewell, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 25 January 1890. (Folder 2)
      This letter acknowledges receipt of the resolutions passed by the citizens of Williamsburg and James City County on the death of Jefferson Davis. (See Jefferson Davis Papers.)
    - Deas (George), at Richmond, Virginia, to Col. B. S. Ewell, at Williamsburg, Virginia, 28 June 1861. (Folder 2)
    - Dickinson (Asa D.), clerk of Hampden Sidney Church, 27 September 1846. (Folder 2)
      A certificate of dismission of Benjamin S. Ewell from Hampden Sidney Church and of recommendation to the church at Lexington, Virginia.
    - Dickinson (Asa D.), at Prince Edward County Court House, to B. S. Ewell, at Lexington, Virginia (On same sheet.), 11 April 1847. (Folder 2)
    - Dimmock (Charles), at Richmond, Virginia, to Prof. George E. Dabney, at Richmond, 8 June 1854. (Folder 2)
      This letter contains an extract from the Register of the Graduates of the U.S. Military Academy, 1850.
    - Donovan (John B.), at Mathews Courthouse, Virginia, to Col. Benjamin S. Ewell, 5 January 1893. (Folder 2)
    - Douglas (Joan) to Elizabeth Ewell, 19 January 1859. (Folder 2)
    - Drew (William), Todd County, Kentucky, to Beverley B. Lowndes, at Lee Town, Jefferson County, Virginia, 2 November 1834. (Folder 2)
    - Dulany (Anne) to Miss [ ? ] Lowndes, at Bladensburg, Prince George's County, Maryland, 11 Aug 1784. (Folder 2)
  - Letters: E, 1784-1934 (Folder 3-10)
    - Eastman, (S.), at West Point, New York, to whom it may concern, 11 November 1838. (Folder 3)
    - Emerson (D. H.), at York, Pennsylvania, to Elizabeth Ewell, daughter of Benjamin S. Ewell., 2 items.
      - Letter, 11 December 1854. (Folder 3)
      - Letter, 18 December 1854. (Folder 3)
    - Letters from Benjamin S. Ewell, April 1830-May 1898., 112 items. (Folder 3-5)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at West Point, New York, to Paul H. Ewell, at Buckland, Prince William County, Virginia, 1 April 1830. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (B. S.), at West Point, New York, to Rebecca L. Ewell, at Bladensburgh, Prince George's County, Maryland, 10 April 1830. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (B. S.), at West Point, to Rebecca L. Ewell, at Buckland, Prince William County, Virginia, March-June 1831., 2 items (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 4 March 1831. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 15 June 1831. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (B. S.), at West Point, to his uncle, William Stoddert, at Jackson, Madison County, Tennessee, 7 December 1834. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (B. S.), at West Point, to Rebecca L. Ewell, at Bladensburgh, Prince George's County, Maryland, October 1835-May 1836., 3 items (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 4 October 1835. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 22 November 1835. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 22 May 1836. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (B. S.), at York, Pennsylvania, to Rebecca L. Ewell, at Greenwich, Prince William County, Virginia, April-September 1837., 2 items. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 23 April 1837. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 10 September 1837. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at West Point, New York, to Rebecca L. Ewell, at Bladensburgh, Prince George's County, Maryland, 28 February 1838. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (B. S.), at York, Pennsylvania, to Rebecca L. Ewell, at Bladensburgh, Prince George's County, Maryland, 10 June 1838. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Baltimore, to Rebecca L. Ewell, at Georgetown, D.C., 12 July 1850. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Williamsburg, Virginia, to Rebecca L. Ewell, 24 November 1851. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Williamsburg, Virginia, to Rebecca L. Ewell, at Washington City, D.C., 16 December 1851. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Williamsburg, Virginia, to his daughter, Elizabeth S. Ewell, 4 November 1859. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Williamsburg, Virginia, to his sister, Elizabeth Ewell, 30 December 1859. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Williamsburg, Virginia, to John Letcher, Governor of Virginia, 23 February 1862. (Folder 3)
        Answer by S. Bassett French, aide de camp, dated 26 February 1862, on back of sheet.
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Richmond, to his daughter, Elizabeth S. Ewell, June-November 1862., 4 items. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 25 June 1862. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 9 July 1862. (Folder 3)
          Note: Map of Richmond and vicinity on back of letter.
        - Letter, 16 October 1862. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 5 November 1862. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Richmond, Virginia, to Bessie [ ? ], 28 November 1862. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Chattanooga, Tennessee, to his daughter, Elizabeth S. Ewell, at Richmond, Virginia, 10 December 1862. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Chattanooga, Tennessee, to his daughter, Elizabeth S. Ewell, December 1862-March 1863. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 18 December 1862. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 24 December 1862. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 28 February 1863. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 4 March 1863. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Tullahoma, Tennessee, to his daughter, Elizabeth S. Ewell, April-May 1863. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 9 April 1863. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 4 May 1863. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Montgomery, Alabama, to his daughter, Elizabeth S. Ewell, 16 May 1863. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Jackson, Mississippi, to his daughter, Elizabeth S. Ewell, at Richmond, Virginia, 9 July 1863. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Camp near Morton, Mississippi, to Elizabeth S. Ewell, 23 July 1863. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Camp near Morton, Mississippi, to Elizabeth S. Ewell, at Richmond, Virginia, 29 July 1863. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Camp near Morton, Mississippi, to Elizabeth S. Ewell, 5 September 1863. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Meridian, Mississippi, to Elizabeth S. Ewell, September-October 1863. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 28 September 1863. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 14 October 1863. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Dalton, Georgia, to his daughter, Elizabeth S. Ewell, at Richmond, Virginia, 31 December 1863. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Dalton, Georgia, to his daughter, Elizabeth S. Ewell, January-February 1864., 3 items. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 16 January 1864. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 28 January 1864. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 17 February 1864. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Atlanta, Georgia, to Elizabeth S. Ewell, April 1864., 2 items (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 4 April 1864. (Folder 3)
        - Letter, 30 April 1864. (Folder 3)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Williamsburg, Virginia, to Elizabeth S. Ewell, his sister, 6 April 1865. (Folder 4)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Fort Warren, to his sister, Rebecca L. Ewell, 18 April 1865. (Folder 4)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Richmond, to Rebecca L. Ewell, 20 June 1865. (Folder 4)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Richmond, to Thomas Tasker Gantt, at St. Louis, Missouri, 6 August 1865. (Folder 4)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.) to Mrs. L. C. Ewell, 27 September 1865. (Folder 4)
      - Ewell (Benjamin S.), at Williamsburg, Virginia, to his sister, Elizabeth S. Ewell, 21 November 1865. (Folder 4)